Guide to the Kenneth M. Reardon papers, 1971-2015.
Reardon, Kenneth M. papers
- Series III. Conferences and Consulting
  - Consulting: Community Plans, Papers, and Studies
    - General
      - Contract, 1988 - 2003 (Box 4, Folder 27)
        Proposal Transmittal Form. Grant Approval Letter. Final Report. Outline. Case Study. Memorandum. Agenda. Notes. Drawings. "The Washington Administration Neighborhood and Economic Development Papers: A Proposal to Establish an Archive" Submitted to the Chicago Community Trust by Center for Urban Economic Development. The University of Illinois at Chicago and the Chicago Historical Society.
      - Contracts, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 28)
        Award Summary. Grant Documents. Budget. Key Personnel Report.
      - Christopherson Report, March 3, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 29)
        Draft for Reviewing Stakeholders. " Economic and Workforce Development and the Optics, Imaging and Photonics Industry in Rochester, New York: Building a 21st Century Industry with a Workforce of the Future"
      - Case Studies, 2001, Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
        "Northwest Bronx Community and Clergy Coalition"; "The Resurrection Project, Chicago, Illinois"; " Alternative Models of Community-based Planning and Development. Reclaiming Woodland: A Collaborative Effort by ACORN and Oakland Residents to Create a Community School" (Working Paper"; "NorthEast Neighborhood Alliance, Rochester, NY."; "The Fifth Avenue Committee"; "Everett Borough Comprehensive Plan" Bedford County, Pennsylvania. (First and Second Draft); "Finding a Way When Things Fall Apart: How Residents of East St. Louis' Emerson Park Neighorhood Turned ther Community Around" by Kenneth M. Reardon. (2 drafts.)
      - CIC Proposal Review Contract, 2000 - 2002 (Box 4, Folder 31)
        Cornell College Site Visit Report. Engaging Communities and Campuses. Correspondence.
    - Annie E. Casey Foundation
      - Design for Casey Report, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Case Study Reading Guidelines, 2003, Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
        Chicago the Resurrection Project. East St. Louis Emerson Park Development Corporation. Everett Tenley Park. Oakland Woodland School. Rochester NorthEast Neighborhood Alliance. Savannah Grant for Blocks.
      - Interim Report, 2001 - 2002 (Box 4, Folder 22)
        "Support the development of a variety of tools and models for neighborhood development planning that residents, neighborhood developers and local officials can easily apply."
      - Proposal, 2001 - 2002, Undated. (Box 4, Folder 23)
        Alternative Community-Based Planning. Correspondence. Budget. Proposal. Meeting Summary. Survey.
      - Final Report, 2003 - 2004 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - The Fifth Avenue Committee. Brooklyn, New York., February 18, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - A Rochester Conversation on Alternative Models of Community-Based Planning and Development, March 20 - 23, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 14)
        Includes Annie E. Casey Foundation Case Studies and a profile on participating organizations
    - Ford Foundation
      - Preliminary Grant, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - June 2003 Report, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Illinois Case Study, Ford PAR, Undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Human Subjects, Undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Human Subjects Approval, February 10, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - Reports and Correspondence, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Contracts, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 38)
        Community Development PAR. Preliminary Project Findings/Possible Future Directions. Participatory Action Research Project.
      - Case Study Possibilities, Undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Choosing of Cases, Undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
        Principles of Best Practice for Alternative Models of Community-Based Planning.
      - Budget, OSP, 2002 - 2003 (Box 4, Folder 41)
        Community Development PAR.
      - Annotated Bibliography, Undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Proposal Network of Higher Educational Institutions. Action Research Projects. Summary., Undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Umass Tape, Undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Case Study Outlines, Undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Proposal Update, Undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Proposal. Team Meetings, February 13, 2002, Undated. (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Survey, 2003, 1997 - 2003 (Box 4, Folder 48)
        Neighborhood Leadership Academy Session Schedule and Description. Questions for Faculty. Web-based survey. Blank participation letters for survey.
      - Proposal, February 2003 - March 2003, Undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
        Preliminary Project Findings/ Possible Future Directions Ford Foundation/ Participatory Action Research Project Notes from Staff Discussion. Preliminary Ideas Domestic Poverty Programs.
- Series IV. Major Projects
  - Cornell Field Study, 1984-1990
    - Legislative Proclamation Honoring Cornell University Field Study Program., February 14, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Press (Field Study), 1985 - 1988 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      The Boston Globe - "NYC Market's Merchants Fear City Sellout"; New York Newsday Articles - "Yuppified Lower E. Side?"; Dennis Duggan, "Merchants' Fears of Yuppie Invasion"; "Snowdown on Essex St. Vendors fear city's plans to rehab market"; "Manhattan Firm to Run Lower East Side Market"; Daily News - "New Boss on Delancy"; Queens Ledger - "Drug Task Force Plans to Fight a 'War' in CB 5"; Field Study Program Newsletters; Field and International Study Program Newsletter; Field Study: A year in Perspective. Ithaca, NY
    - Field Study Program Newsletter, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Manhattan Valley: The Forgotten Neighborhood. Critical Issues Project., May 21, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Architecture Art and Planning Newsletter article on Utica Planning Workshop., Spring 1984 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Cornell Daily Sun - "CU Students conduct study of healthcare", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Essex Street Market Improvement Report - "Insuring the Future of the Essex Street Market: A Business & Financial Plan", May 1987 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Field Study of Essex St. Market Report, January 1987 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Drug Abuse Study presented to the Leadership Task-force Queens Community Board 5, December 11, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Substance Abuse Among Youth in the Rockaways, May 1986 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign: East St. Louis Project, 1990 - 1999
    - Edgemont Plan, May 1995 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      This plan was created to provide a framework for the Edgement Citizens for Crime Prevention and Community Development to develop future projects, and includes a historic and present (1995) context of the Edgemont neighborhood; authored by two of Professor Reardon's master's students (Ricardo A. Alarcón and Damon Y. Smith) in collaboration with residents of Edgemont and the East St. Louis Action Revitalization Project Prepared for and in cooperation with the Edgemont Citizens for Crime Prevention & Community Development. University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Department of Urban and Regional Planning.
    - Emerson Park. Proposal and Preliminary Findings for Neighborhood Improvement Plan (NIP), Fall 1990 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      The preliminary findings and outline on the Emerson Park neighborhood which was soon transformed into a complete Neighborhood Improvement Plan (NIP) five months later; also included is a proposal for an Emerson Park Action Research Project by the university's Neighborhood Planning Workshop presented to the Emerson Park Neighborhood Coalition, the beginnings of the Emerson Park Neighborhood Improvement Plan; also contains a contact list for Emerson Park stakeholders and Emerson Park Institutional Interview Mailing List.
    - Emerson Park NIP, May 1991 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      Catalogues deteriorating neighborhood conditions and presents directives for addressing such conditions. Census Data for Emerson Park/ Selected Areas from 1960's - 1990. The Emerson Park Plans include Neighborhood Improvement Plan for Emerson Park (1991), Community Safety Plan for Emerson Park (1992) and Emerson Community Development Block Grant Program (1992-1997). Population and Housing in Emerson Park. Emerson Park Research Project.
    - Emerson Park Community Safety Plan, February 25, 1991 - May 1992 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      This plan was created as a guide to coordinate the efforts of local residents, law enforcement officials and public officials in improving neighborhood safety. An executive summary of the plan in addition to correspondence with the U.S. Department of Justice Drug Enforcement Administration regarding the East St. Louis Crime Prevention Project are included.
    - Emerson Park Community Development Block Grant Program Proposal, May 15, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Emerson Park Neighborhood Summit Materials, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Neighborhood Technical Assistance Center (NTAC), October 16, 1998 - July 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Funding proposal for the Neighborhood Technical Assistance Center as operated by the university Board of Trustees; draft budget amendment for Fiscal Year 1998/1999 for the Neighborhood Technical Assistance Center.
    - NTAC Materials, 1996 - 1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Includes examples of materials that were housed in the NTAC including East St. Louis Action Research Project (ESLARP) annual reports and overviews and a Request for Assistance form which includes a summary of NTAC's mission and program activities
    - Empowerment Zones/Enterprise Communities ESL Application for Designation Materials, June 28, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Correspondence. "Regional Empowerment Zone. Building the Bridge". Community Profiles for Greater East St. Louis Enterprise Communities. Population and Housing Data (1960 - 1997) Booklets. Application materials for Empowerment Zone or Enterprise Community designation for the Greater St. Louis region; materials include a letter from Illinois Governor Jim Edgar to the Secretary of HUD, community profiles and projects for Greater St. Louis, which specifically includes Emerson Park in the Neighborhood/Community Development Implementation Projects section, and population and housing profiles for Greater East St. Louis.
    - Community School Sites Proposal, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Proposal for community schools as places to improve health care for children and families, to reduce crime especially among young people, and to increase recreational programs for children in four targeted areas in East St. Louis; partial plan only.
    - Emerson Park Revitalization Plan, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lansdowne Neighborhood Improvement Plan, 1991 -April 1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      This comprehensive community development initiative focuses on employment, housing, public safety, municipal, and social services needs of the Lansdowne Neighborhood laying-out a five-year development strategy; first year programming on affordable housing, open space planning, and employment initiatives; Lansdowne Neighborhood Research Project summary of findings also included. The Lansdowne Community Development Block Grant Proposal 1992 - 1996. A Five Year Plan for the Lansdowne Awareness Community Committee. Neighborhood Improvement Plan for Lansdowne.
    - Olivette Park Historic District, 1977 - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      National Register of Historic Places Nomination Packet for places in the Olivette Park neighborhood and contributions to a neighborhood historic district
    - Olivette Park Neighborhood Summit, February 10, 1996 - August 15, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Neighborhood Summit packet for an attendee, including an agenda, handouts on the goals for the summit, an evaluation form for feedback on the summit, a SWOT analysis from the Olivette Park Action Revitalization Plan, Olivette Park Neighborhood Association and other neighborhood stakeholder contact information
    - Katherine Dunham Dynamic Museum, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      The museum is named after and filled with the art collections of Katherine Dunham, an East St. Louis institutional leader. The museum is located in within the Pennsylvania awards Avenue Historic District in a building on the Illinois Historic Registry and was directly tied into the Cultural Redevelopment District Plan. This museum houses Ms. Dunham's collection of African, West African, and South American art, inclusive of Ms. Dunham's costumes, photography, programs, letters, awards, and mementos from her career as a dancer, choreographer, teacher, and dance company owner.
    - East St. Louis Revitalization Project, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Vol. 3: Faculty and Student Projects, comprised of contributions from UIUC School of Architecture, covers a variety of planning topics specific to east St. Louis, including GIS mapping, fundraising, computer based planning assessment tools, industrial development, land use strategies, housing, and transportation University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Department of Urban and Regional Planning.
    - East St. Louis Action Research Project (ESLARP) Report, Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - ESLARP: Annual Reports and Project Summaries, 1993 - 1998 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - ESLARP Press, 1993 - 1999, Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Articles about or mentioning ESLARP in The New Public Innovator; a piece written by Ed Wisneski from Southern Methodist University; "Participatory Action Research in East St. Louis" written by a UIUC graduate student Kirk Goodrich and Ph.D. student Lucia Resende, Spring 1993. Also included are an informational pamphlet about ESLARP; a flyer advertising an event "Community Revitalization along the Mississippi," sponsored by ESLARP and featuring Dr. Reardon as a speaker; flyer for the Downtown Community Forum, "City Back From The Edge: Creating University/Community Partnerships"; flyers publicizing ESLARP and Egrets, an online geographic information guide for East St. Louis.
    - ESLARP Press II, 1996 - 1999 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      "Trustees Approve More than $2 Billion Operating Budget; Alumni News Volume 20. College of Fine and Applied Arts. University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Department of Urban and Regional Planning; Flyers for "Phil Gramm's War on CRA. Analysis & Commentary); COPC (Community Outreach Partnership Centers) Central. "Colleges and Universities work well with CDBG"; "University Accepts Challenge to Revive a City"; "A Sustainable Community/ University Partnership" by Kenneth M. Reardon; State of the States "One Poor City's 'Awesome; Project"; Correspondence. ESLARP Booklets.
    - ESLARP Press - Neal R. Pierce, Undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
      State of the States "One Poor City's 'Awesome; Project"; Washington Post Article "University-Community Breakthrough in East St. Louis. University of Illinois makes a 'best practice' of East St. Louis, helping students and residents".
    - "Growing East St. Louis" Poster, Undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - East St. Louis Handouts, Undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Flyers and Press, 1993 - 1997, Undated. (Box 5, Folder 20)
      Articles include Inside Illinois - "Martin"; The Champaign-Urbana news-Gazette - "City to Start Group in Garden Hills"; "Students' work gives E. St. Louis children place to play"; Connections, East St. Louis Action Research Project - "Riches Amidst the Rubble of East St. Louis"; East St. Louis Farmers' Market brochure.
    - ESLARP: Neighborhoods Conditions Survey, August 1996 - January 1999 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Reestablishing Municipal Planning and Design, August 4, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - City History and Economic Baseline Reports, 1992 - 1999 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      Background information about East St. Louis economy, government, and general history of the city.
    - Demographs 1960- 1997, 1960 - 1977 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      Demographic information about race, labor, population change, unemployment, income, household and more.
    - Articles Related to ESL About Planning and Partcipation, 1966, Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
      "Patterns of Community Development by Richard Franklin; "The Context for Planning in East St. Louis"
    - EZ/EC Proposal, Undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - East St. Louis Consolidated Plan 1995-1999, June 1995 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Bond for Deed Survey Instruments and Interview Notes, Fall 1994 (Box 5, Folder 29)
      Survey instruments for interviewing Winstanley Neighborhood residents, institutional stakeholders, and other stakeholders in regards to how bond for deed affects properties and interviewees; in addition to bond for deed, there is a housing survey, interview agendas, guidelines, and notes. Interviews and surveys were conducted, and materials were created for and/or by the Community Planning Workshop.
    - Bond for Deed Winstanley/Industry Park Neighborhood Outreach Materials, September 1994 (Box 5, Folder 30)
      Public service, press release, fact sheets, and other outreach materials to Winstanley/Industry Park Neighborhood Organization (WIPNO) and all East St. Louis residents interested in or involved in bond for deed contracts to engage the community in a Housing Improvement Campaign, a community education and outreach campaign. Also included in this folder are Professor Reardon's personal notes on the impacts of bond-for-deed in East St. Louis
    - Bond for Deed Government and Legislative Advocacy, August 1994 - October 1994 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      Documents include existing Illinois state ordinance in regards to regulation of sales of dwelling structure by installment sales contracts and the history of the ordinance, related laws; a proposal for contract for deed reform from Illinois state Senator Rosson; and a memo from the Illinois Governor Jim Edgar's office regarding the legislation put forth by state Representative Wyvetter Younge (D-East St. Louis) specifically to require the seller of real estate property by installment contract to provide proper notices, tax bills concerning the property being transferred to the purchaser, and that the contract be recorded, lest the contract seller assume liability for any damages resulting in failure to record the contract. The document from the Governor's office also includes a brief bill analysis. Additional law review resources.
    - Bond-for-Deed in the News, 1993 - 1996 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - ESLARP Strategic Planning Notes; Committee, 1998 - 1999 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - ESLARP Organizational Chart, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "Developers' Guide to Affordable Housing in East St. Louis", May 5, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Community Organization Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Chapters included are: Direct Action, Selecting and Researching Winnable Issues, Understanding Power, Organizing Public Actions, Stop the Press: Working the media, Fundraising and Basics of Organizational Finance, Recruitment and Outreach, Conducting Effective Meetings,
    - East St. Louis Community Action Network (ESLCAN) - Community Outreach Partnership Centers Program, 1998 - 1999, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - ESL CAN Community Organizing, Training Seminar, Materials and Notes., March 24, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Crime Prevention Through Environmental Design (CPTED), Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Community Outreach Partnership Centers (COPC) Program 2-yr Proposal, March 14, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Proposal to expand on the ESLARP successes and community outreach; specifically to expand planning and program implementation capacity, continue the neighborhood college, establish a neighborhood technical assistance center, and a research project on the best strategies for dealing with depopulating small cities like East St. Louis.
    - COPC Program Revisions and Updates I and II, August 8, 1995 - October 15, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Metro East COPC Proposal, June 8, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      A funding proposal expanding the services of the Neighborhood Technical Assistance Center and citizen organization, economic and housing development.
    - Alta Sita Neighborhood Summit and Community Participation Materials, April 17, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Planning materials, invitations and contact list, neighborhood SWOT analysis based on interviews with neighborhood residents, development plan outlines for feedback, and other preparatory materials/notes.
    - Winstanley Industry Park Neighborhood Improvement Plan (WIPNIP), July 1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Describes current neighborhood conditions and views of local residents; lays out a 5-year strategic plan to stabilize the area, addressing topics such as health and safety interventions, infrastructure improvements, housing, urban design, employment and economic development, crime reduction,, and the recommended implementation of new city-wide and regional policies.
    - Winstanley Industry Park Neighborhood Organization (WIPNO) proposals and community participation materials, August 1992 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Summary/ abbreviated version of the WIPNIP; WIPNO membership brochures (3); WIPNO resident perceptions survey; WIPNO Home Ownership Information Finance Initiative (HIFI),; attachments pertaining to WIPNO home improvement programs, Woman With Children First housing initiative project narrative
    - Land Contracts, January 1995 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Looks at the prevalence and the advantages/disadvantage of the use of installment land contracts as an instrument used in lieu of traditional mortgages to buy homes in East St. Louis and makes recommendations for future regulation of the installment land contract market
    - WIPNO Block Grant Proposal, September 1992 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Empowerment Planning in East St. Louis: A People's Struggle for Local Democracy" by Ken Reardon, September 2002 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Describes the 15 year experience of working in a University-community partnership in East St. Louis, including major achievements, challenges, and lessons learned.
    - (Early) Articles by Kenneth Reardon, November 1991 - September 2002 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Articles by Kenneth Reardon and Others, 1999, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - East St. Louis Action Research Project and Materials, 1993-1999 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Affordable Houseing Guides, 1997, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - List of Kenneth M. Reardon's Publications for the East St. Louis Action Research Project (ESLARP), Undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Press, 1996 - 1999 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Press, 1992-2000 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - ESL CAN Materials and General Community Organizing Guides., c. 2001 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - UP378: Neighborhood Maps, 1998, Undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Community Organizing, 1992 - 1999, Undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
      Includes ESLARP, The Lansdowne Development, Crime Prevention Initiatives, Community Organizing and Victory in St. Louis, press, correspondence, notes, proposals, materials, conference.
    - Reports, Memos, and Meeting Agendas, 1994-1998 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - State and Local Government Class - Neighborhood College, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - "Participatory Action Research in St. Louis" by Kirk Goodrich and Lucia Resende, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Introduction to Giving Hope Video: Dedication of Temple Buell Hall by Kenneth Reardon, October 13, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - NTAC Reports, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Katherine Dunham Dynamic Museum fundraising materials, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - A Recreation Program and Implementation Proposal for the Winstanley/Industry Park Neighborhood, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Community Planning and Design Center for East St. Louis, Illinois, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - "Common Ground: Creating a Comprehensive Plan for Community Development in East St. Louis, Illinois", 1992 (Box 6, Folder 31)